Sukanya Kannan Moudgalya

У @SukMoudgalya

Google Scholar

https://sukanyam.github.io/

Research Mission

I am an educational researcher focusing on socially-just Computer Science (CS) and technology education. Socially-just Computer Science and Technology education (like Culturally Responsive Computing) has mostly been researched in informal contexts. I aim to extend the research in formal K-12 contexts by (1) studying teacher preparation, (2) disrupting whiteness in CS and tech-fields, (3) designing tech-tools meant for civic participation, (4) studying the impact of anti-racist technology education on youth, and (5) connecting informal and formal spaces of learning anti-racist technologies.

Education

2017 - 2022

Ph.D., Michigan State University Educational Psychology and Educational Technology Thesis title: Teachers navigating Whiteness in Computer Science to Support Youth Civic Participation

Committee Members: Dr. Aman Yadav (Advisor), Dr. Michael Lachney, Dr. Joanna Goode, Dr. Terrance Burgess

2015 - 2017

M.A., The University of Texas at Austin Learning Technologies

Thesis title: Strategies to improve collaboration in a problem-based learning environment:

Alien Rescue

2010 – 2014 **B.S., SASTRA University (TN, India)** Biotechnology

Employment History

2021 – .. **Equity-Focused Graduate Assistant** Michigan State University, College of Education I lead equity centered efforts in terms of educational workshop sessions, course reforms, and program requirements in my Ph.D. program

2017 - 2022

Graduate Research and Teaching Assistant Michigan State University, College of Education

I have been a research assistant in an NSF-funded project (IntroCS-POGIL). I also taught various courses in undergraduate and graduate levels through various modalities.

2016 – 2017 Graduate Research Assistant Office of Instructional Innovation, College of Education, UT Austin

2016 Data Science Intern McGraw Hill Education, Boston

Junior Research Fellow. Tutorials for Cervical Cancer Screening and Pap Smear in India, Indian Institute of Technology (I.I.T.) Bombay, India

Awards and Achievements

- (\$1,000) Research Practicum/Dissertation Development Fellowship, Michigan State University, College of Education
- 2017-2022 (\$90,000) Erickson Research Fellowship, Michigan State University, College of Education
 - (\$2,000) Various Conference Travel Fellowships, Michigan State University, College of Education and the Graduate School
 - 2017 (\$4,000) University CUMREC Fellowship, Michigan State University, The Graduate School
 - 2014 (\$500) Desh-Videsh Scholarship, SASTRA University
- 2010-2014 (INR 30,000) Dean's Merit List, SASTRA University

Research Publications

Peer-Reviewed Journal Articles

- Allen, M., Green, B., Lachney, M., **Moudgalya**, **S. K.**, & Robinson, C. (n.d.). Seeding Equity: Using Adinkra to Seed an Equity Ethic in US Urban STEM Education. (*Under Review in Urban Education*).
- Moudgalya, S. K., Lachney, M., Yadav, A., & Allen, M. (n.d.). Doubly White: Exploring White Computer Science Teachers Ideas about Culture, Community, and Responsiveness in their Classrooms. (*Under Review* in the Journal of Teacher Education).
- Lachney, M., Bennett, A. G., Eglash, R., Yadav, A., & **Moudgalya**, **S. K.** (2021). Teaching in an open village: a case study on culturally responsive computing in compulsory education. *Computer Science Education*, 1–27.

Peer-Reviewed Conference Papers**

- Mayfield, C., **Moudgalya**, **S. K.**, Yadav, A., Kussmaul, C., & Hu, H. H. (2022). POGIL in CS1: Evidence for Student Learning and Belonging. In *Proceedings of the 53rd ACM Technical Symposium on Computer Science Education* (SIGCSE).
- Moudgalya, S. K., Mayfield, C., Yadav, A., Hu, H. H., & Kussmaul, C. (2021). Measuring Students' Sense of Belonging in Introductory CS Courses. In *Proceedings of the 52nd ACM Technical Symposium on Computer Science Education* (SIGCSE) (pp. 445–451).
- Moudgalya, S. K., Yadav, A., Sands, P., Vogel, S., & Zamansky, M. (2021). Teacher Views on Computational Thinking as a Pathway to Computer Science. In Proceedings of the 26th ACM Conference on Innovation and Technology in Computer Science Education V. 1 (ITiCSE) (pp. 262–268).
- Yadav, A., Mayfield, C., **Moudgalya, S. K.**, Kussmaul, C., & Hu, H. (2021). Collaborative Learning, Self-Efficacy, and Student Performance in CS1 POGIL. In *Proceedings of the 52nd ACM Technical Symposium on Computer Science Education* (SIGCSE) (pp. 775–781).
- Moudgalya, S. K., Rich, K. M., Yadav, A., & Koehler, M. J. (2019). Computer Science Educators Stack Exchange: Perceptions of Equity and Gender Diversity in Computer Science. In *Proceedings of the 50th ACM Technical Symposium on Computer Science Education* (SIGCSE) (pp. 1197–1203).

^{***}SIGCSE, ITICSE, and ICER are Association of Computing Machinery (ACM) conferences and are considered to be equivalent to journal articles in Computer Science (CS) in terms of rigorous peer-review. See reference here. "A distinctive feature of CS publication is the importance of selective conferences and books. Journals do not necessarily carry more prestige"

Lightly-Reviewed Conference Papers and Presentations

- Sands, P., Moudgalya, S. K., & Yadav, A. (2021). Teacher Beliefs about CT Integration in K-5 Curriculum. American Educational Research Association (AERA) Annual Meeting, Virtual. American Educational Research Association (AERA) Annual Meeting, Virtual, American Educational Research Association (AERA).
- Moudgalya, S. K. (2020). Online sharing practices in a computer science education discussion forum. American educational research association (AERA) Annual Meeting. American Educational Research Association (AERA) (Conference was canceled due to the COVID 19 pandemic).
- Moudgalya, S. K., & Willet, K. B. S. (2019). Communities and Clusters: User Interactions in an Online Discussion Forum for Computer Science Education. Society for Information Technology & Teacher Education International Conference (SITE), 2291–2298. Association for the Advancement of Computing in Education (AACE).
- Willet, K. B. S., & Moudgalya, S. K. (2019). Community, network, or space: Conceptualizing inspired professional learning in an online discussion forum. Association for Educational Communications and Technology (AECT) International Convention. Association for Educational Communications and Technology (AECT).
- Willet, B. S., Moudgalya, S. K., Boltz, L., Greenhalgh, S., & Koehler, M. (2018). Back to the gaming board: Understanding games and education through board game reviews. Society for Information Technology & Teacher Education International Conference (SITE), 495-503. Association for the Advancement of Computing in Education (AACE).

Doctoral Consortium

Moudgalya, S. K. (2019). Educator Supports in Broadening Participation in Computing. In *Proceedings* of the 2019 ACM Conference on International Computing Education Research (ICER) (pp. 343–344).

Invited Talks and Presentations

Moudgalya, S. K. (2021). Measuring students' sense of belonging in introductory cs courses. COMPUTE 2021, Virtual, Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) India Council.

Grant Applications

- (Applied, in review: \$12,000) Creating Inclusive Excellence Grant (CIEG), Michigan State 2021 University; Title: Exploring Whiteness and Culturally Responsive Computing with High-school Computer Science teachers. Applicants: Sukanya Moudgalya and Dr. Aman Yadav. Role: Lead writing efforts for the project, based on my dissertation.
 - (Assisted, Granted \$999,678) National Science Foundation, Title: Collaborative Research: Moving beyond access increasing teacher knowledge to teach rigorous equity-focused high school computing. Recipients: PI at Michigan State: Dr. Aman Yadav, Co-PI: Dr. Michael Lachney. PI at University of Detroit-Mercy: Dr. Richard Hill Role: Assisted with writing efforts and gathered resources and citations.

Teaching

6 semesters

■ CEP 416: Teaching and Learning with Technologies. Michigan State University, College of Education

This course is an 400 level **undergraduate introductory course to Educational Technology**. This course discusses Design Thinking, Equity and Technology, Social Media, Media and Information Literacy, Coding and Computational Thinking, etc, in order to facilitate integration of technology in the future classrooms of the pre-service teachers. I have taught it in two modes: **online asynchronous and hybrid (online/in-person)**

2 semesters

■ CEP 807: Capstone in Educational Technology Michigan State University, College of Education

This course is an 800 level **masters/graduate capstone course**. This capstone focuses on the masters students showcasing the projects and artifacts they make during the their entire program by creating digital portfolios. I have taught it in **online asynchronous** mode

1 semester

TE 150: Reflections on Learning Michigan State University, College of Education This course is an 100 level undergraduate introductory course to Educational Psychology. Pre-service teachers learn and reflect on the research behind human learning and development. I cover topics such as theories of learning, motivation, culture and global perspectives, and equity as they relate to teaching in K-12 classrooms. I have taught it in in-person mode

Service

- Graduate Student Representative (Elected) Educational Psychology and Educational Technology
 - **Reviewer** The Annual Conference on Research in Equity and Sustained Participation in Engineering, Computing, and Technology (RESPECT 21')
- 2020 Reviewer ACM Conference on Innovation and Technology in Computer Science Education (ITiCSE '20)
- 2019 Reviewer ACM Technical Symposium on Computer Science Education (SIGCSE '19)
 - **Student Organizer** The Annual Conference for the Society for Information Technology and Teacher Education (SITE '19)
- Sub-reviewer Educational Data Mining (EDM '17) and Artificial Intelligence in Education (AIED '17)
 - Student Organizer The Annual Conference for the Society for Information Technology and Teacher Education (SITE '17)
- 2016 Student Recruitment Volunteer Volunteering to spend time (in both panel discussions and 1:1 meetings) with potential students to Michigan State University and the University of Texas at Austin

Miscellaneous Experience

Mentoring and Peer Assistance

Research Practicum Mentor/Practicum Committee Student Member. Mr. Zac Opps (Ph.D. Candidate at MSU) Practicum: Who Belongs in the Computer Science Classroom?

2017-.. Peer Assistance. Providing reliability coding services (in qualitative coding) for Research Practicums (2) and Doctoral Dissertation (1).

Peer Mentoring. Mentoring South Asian women to apply to U.S. graduate schools in Social Sciences and STEM fields (4)

2016 Academic Mentor UT Austin Athletics Department.

Certification

2020 Certificate in Online College Teaching. Michigan State University, College of Education

ID Verified Certificate in DAT203.1x: Data Science Essentials. Awarded by edX and Microsoft.

ID Verified Certificate in 11.133x: Implementation and Evaluation of Educational Technology. Awarded by edX and MITx.

Honor Code Certificate in 11.132x: Design and Development of Educational Technology.

Awarded by edX and MITx.

Memberships

American Educational Research Association (AERA)

Association for Computing Machinery (ACM)

Special Interest Group in Computer Science Education (SIGCSE)

Skills

Languages | English, Tamil, Hindi

Coding/Statistical Software R Statistics, SPSS, Tableau, Lagrange R Statistics, SPSS, SPS

Qualitative Software NVivo, RQDA

Educational Software Adobe Captivate, Canvas LMS

Misc. Academic research, teaching, and publishing.